foreign material so
so
in his note on Pasa he says
on account of their structural
similarity well I'll say what those two
things are in a moment these two
independent patterns appear one
superimposed on the other and when
there's failure to distinguish between
these patterns the subject comes to be
identified with the eye
those term those two patterns being both
in visual experience forms are seen the
eye is unseen
and in quite a different way he says
objects are seen the subject is unseen
I don't necessarily have a specific
question about that but
a good place to
begin the conversation maybe about like
practically you read that
what does what what is to be done on
account of that you know
yeah so I mean it's it's a
it's a correct description but it is
sort of the um
it's a description that kind of pertains
to the end of it
when you when um
seeing that pattern that's not how you
start to kind of build it up towards seeing
to kind of build it up towards seeing
the pattern that's the
that can be a potential problem if
somebody just reads that and tries to
figure it out
because uh subject object for example
see you can be thinking now about aha
right objects objects not seen but
you're doing that on your own terms
that already the experience of doing
that is something that you're
subjectively taking unaware of you as a
subject there and then
so in other words you you're sort of
contemplating what he said but at the
arm's length
so um instead of trying to figure it out
until it makes sense in that way more
like try to tailor okay so do I know
do I see the subject he's talking about
do I see that as a phenomenon
do I see that negative aspect of it it's
always in the background always slips
through fingers if you try to catch you
know to sort of
kind of put in front of you this sense
of I am sense of subjectivity It's
Always it's always it's always slipping
you so if you try to attend to it
directly it's always elsewhere
so you recognize that it is property so
yes you can then mystify it as people
would do
order as well actually it can be still
understood because it does appear as
such it appears as something that's
always in the background of what I'm looking at
in the background of what I'm looking at
that's just its nature
always is always going to be the
opposite end of wherever you look
so understanding that those properties
seeing it really such as I said before
that's how you get to actually uh
discern that subject
now you know as he describes that sort
of corresponds to eye organs and sites
that you see but really those
comparisons are not
not as important what's important is
that whether you approach it through eye
organ and sites or whether you approach
it like a subject object divide
you follow it through all the way
not just for the sake of comparison and
getting the satisfaction of oh look this
I saw what I saw things that fit that
correspond that's kind of not the point that can
that's kind of not the point that can
sort of encourage you to practice sure
but the measure of fitting the measure
of successful understanding is freedom
from suffering freedom from subjectivity
in that sense
so if you thoroughly understand the uh
there's a basis the sense organ bases
there will be no room for conceit
and whether you actually recognize that
that also corresponds to the subject
object divide or not it's irrelevant
you followed it through
so that's why this is like all these
different approaches
as I said inevitably you'll be drawing
parallels and comparisons and so on but
fundamentally the practices on the level
of following it through
still understanding is developed on
account of it so
till the bases are endured sufficiently
enough descent sufficiently enough understood
descent sufficiently enough understood
as unownable sufficiently enough
or subjectivity is seen as an objective
phenomena not by making it an object but by seeing
not by making it an object but by seeing
it's real as this subjective phenomenon
that's always in the peripheral and such
it's an objective fact that it is there
we certain that is unable discern that
is something that cannot belong to you
cannot be in your control
and then your sense of self will
diminish
so you often translate
um
as pressure which is also quite
practical in the sense yeah yeah I'm
seeing that pressure as a phenomena well
that's that's weird see that's where you
start looking because people same people
who read about pasta contact whatever
you translate it and then they think on
their own terms all right contact and
this happens and it's kind of sort of
laying it out almost like a experiment
in physics sort of thing but it's it's
it's completely not there even if you
make sense of things on that level it's
just there's nothing to do
uh with the dhamma because dhamma only
applies on the level that frees you from
suffering and so where is the suffering while
and so where is the suffering while
suffering is where things are felt and
that's where the pressure is
so ah being pressured being touched
being under a certain weight of feeling
of Aggregates that's pasta
so your contemplation then should never
forget that or put that second
and acting out of that
has to entail
ignoring the puzzle so you might think
the the past has gone away because I'm
I'm acting towards craving or ill yeah so
acting towards craving or ill yeah so
that's that's like initially you know
like the there may be a coarser form of
pressure are gone
are gone
but you recognize that even even a
neutral feeling for as long as you're
not fully free from a video will have a
degree of pressure
so then you just have to define it
but that's that kind of the Practical
side the Practical development is that
like
there is the contemplation there is
collecting information
but fundamentally
the basis
that that is necessary for any of such
manipulation to apply
is is something that needs to be
cultivated beforehand needs to be kind
of
brought up to a certain fulfillment
until it's efficient and then these
things can be seen on that level
and that development that bringing up
the Fulfillment it's exactly that starts
with the sensor strain guarding the
sensors but yeah so knowing
but yeah so knowing
the intentions behind your actions
that's always going to reveal the
pressure as well
so if you're unsure where the pressure
is just ask yourself
what do you want to do
where is your mind leaning towards what
what is it thinking about what is
delighting in you'll find pressure
you'll find the pressure as a as a
general sort of
weather so to speak sending in a certain
direction it doesn't need to be like acutely felt
it doesn't need to be like acutely felt
intense pressure in your chest or
something no it's just any form of that
being under a under a mental under an
emotional kind of um touch so to speak
it's it's contacting you
it's exerting its force on you however
subtle so so that's when you when you when you
so so that's when you when you when you
recognize that right so feeding this
it's what's on wholesome yes of course
as I said the precepts are first taken
in that external level to continue to
continue until you start learning but
once you recognize that the root of
unwholesome is really whether you feed
the craving feed the pressure or not
then like you don't need specific rules
in a way
and you would certainly not be able to
break other rules that are defined because
other rules that are defined because
again you you if you don't act out of
that pressure If you donate out of the
craving you can't do anything on
wholesome and they recognition lies there so it's
and they recognition lies there so it's
like I said that before for example I
don't know
certain things might be acceptable to do
like say
oh you can eat chocolate in the
afternoon that's allowable
it's a it's kind of simple example
it's not against the rules
like they're all permutations or when
they are
all Traditions agree on it it's fine
but you see that you would be doing it
for wrong reasons
wrong reasons
wrong reasons being anything
from boredom
craving for tastes
craving for sugar
and distraction curiosity I don't know
but all those reasons are unnecessary
reasons so
so
recognition here is like that not like
oh I mustn't have these thoughts or
something but it's more on the level of
you recognize that you have such
thoughts you don't act out of them you don't try
you don't act out of them you don't try
to get rid of them
for as long as it takes if like three
weeks later still
the only reason you would eat chocolate
it's still you're unclear about it and
it's still rooted in I just want to try
it I just want to try it you don't do it
five years later
you still don't do it
because that's the criteria
that's that being established in virtue
being established in right criteria that
defines virtue
but then if in two days time
like those reasons are gone
those reasons are gone
and you need to take medicine or you're
sick or something you eat it it's fine
and you will know that it's fine because
you saw where it comes from so that
sense of safety will be recognized
and the mind your own mind possessed by
Mara cannot attack you it will try
but it won't be able to enter you
because you have not acted out of that
suitable basis as in suitable for MATA
basically suitable for Mara's attacks
and that's how you know internally now
what's right or wrong
so I gave the example but you realize
yeah it's on the level of the small
intentions like another typical example would be
like another typical example would be
like I don't know something you hear
something and you want to look in that
direction and before you do it's like
why
now it might be all just whatever
to prevent issues from arising or
something if it's something practical
but it might also be oh well
it might also be oh well
I'm just curious
so you ask her well if you look
out of such reasons curiosity
carelessness is there a chance that last
would invade your mind if you see
something that's inciting or lost
it's like yeah
there's probably a good chance that will
happen because what I'm about to look at
is a group of people men and women
so why would I do that then I won't do
it oh but I no I don't have to look
and then if you do have to look at it
for whatever reason you would look at it
and you wouldn't think twice
and by mean any other reason any other
reason that's not unwholesome if
somebody starts talking to you from that
group you would obviously look and talk back
you would obviously look and talk back
and but see it was not rooted in that
wrong thing all the externally seems the
same there is externally there is no
there is externally there is no
difference in that action either way you
look because you spoke but first time
you looked and spoke because you were
curious or lustful or whatever second
time is because circumstances just
shaped it that way
and there is a whole world of difference
internally speaking
another good example is like when a suit
has often talk about it
like you shouldn't say anything that's
um it's rooted in a version or real will
and before you say something that's
really Innovation or you will you should
reflect where am I free from a version
is this coming from a version
uh to not only the reflect oh is this
true or not is this benefit is this is
this going to benefit the monastery or
not that's that's not a factor that
those are the external factors no no am
I coming out of place available
well what I'm about to say be factually
beneficial for them beneficial for me
beneficial for both
uh if those factors are not met you
don't say it
even if the whole Monastery will sort of
go to ruin as a result of it you don't
say it because your criteria is your
wrong attention intention must not be
fed
and that's something you like you you
would probably you know you'll probably
go through yourself and you might see
others do it always feels Justified like
there's always people will try to apply
this criteria to a certain point
they'll reflect they reflect but then it
will come oh yeah but if I don't say
anything now oh it's gonna have big
repercussions I must say it so then
basically what you effectively do then
is like I must put Buddha's instruction
second and deal with this issue first
and then I'll get back to practicing the
Buddha's instruction
and you realize that's why you never
practice the Buddhist instruction you're
never taking it on because when it comes
too much you put it aside to deal with
it and then bring it back on
and that's not the practice Yeah
I was going to say like
the smallest of intentions will reveal
like the biggest things
you yeah and also like once you start
recognizing those subtle intentions and
then not feeding them the mind will
start to Rebel you then you're going to
realize how Wild of an animal it
actually is how irrational it's going to
become like you've seen who is fine okay it's
like you've seen who is fine okay it's
fine everything fits and my practice is
good like what do I do next but we'll
increase sense restraint start saying no
to yourself a bit more and see if your
mind remains perfectly Economist nothing
has changed congratulations you've
finished your work you're highly
unlikely that that will be the case it's
going to start to Rebel
kick and scream and even the stuff that
was clear and made sense it's all going
to be abandoned and the mind will just
be a redneck animal that's going to try
to force you to act wake you up in the
middle of the night breaking in sweat
just go and act just do it just do it
it's to be completely rational
but the criteria there
by that point if you have been
developing things rightly you'll know
oh so how long will I don't care how
long this lasts
um
my problem is not the fact that the mind
is a wild animal my problem is if I act
out of it and keep enabling it that's
that's why it's
it's my issue if I don't do my part
can it remain screaming and kicking for
the rest of his life
you realize that's still wholesome
because you are not reading it and
obviously it can't remain Kicking and
Screaming the rest of life because once
you as the suit is obtaining the wild
elephant repeats often once you
pin it down stop stop kind of giving in
to its to its whims and pressures
it will kick and scream you're in a
defeat try to kill you and so on but it
will have to come down
if the precepts are there developed
beforehand that will be it's it's a
leather straps keeping it in place and
it will come down and then it will start
to listen and take food and obey
how much that elephant will kick and
scream individually that depends how
much how Wild was it it was before but
as I often say I reckon today for most
people it's probably pretty wild given
the just natural degrees of sensuality
we all proliferated towards
um
so yeah it does boil down to recognizing
the little intentions the little kind of
practical things oh but everybody says
doing this it's fine
the entire tradition says this is fine
look that's how it's done externally I
just do it like everybody else it's like
that's not the measure of wholesome or
and wholesome
that's the that's the basically initial
guideline for somebody who really can't tell
for somebody who really can't tell
where you know what where wholesome
would even begin but if you just stick
to it thinking that's it that's all you
need to do just just externally emulate
wholesome accepted Behavior norms
and not take on the internal criteria as
the actual measure
you are you're not taking on the
practice you're not even starting it so
to speak
and that's the unpleasant part see
because you you can have your mind
revolve around something so silly or
irrational for like four or five days
which is constantly
because you refuse to look
or you refuse to eat that chocolate or
you refuse to to act out that's it
it's like Well yeah if that's what the
Mind does as a result of right course of
action that's where the Mind does I'll just
that's where the Mind does I'll just
focus on the right course of action
you don't need to be or beat this mind
now twice as hard or something
strangle it no just
you know where the Gateway is you know
where the door the threshold is what you
need to protect
so if there is an unwholesome attention
that's what you don't feed you don't
compromise if there is wholesome it's
fine mine gets too late mine gets depressed
mine gets too late mine gets depressed
doesn't matter that secondary
you know it as such
as this is
but generally it's kind of much easier
you know as I said somebody might try to
do a bit but then after a while of that
building up of that irrationality and
doubt and mind trying to pressure you to
act and becoming more kind of seemingly
more sensitive
it's kind of easier to just then fall
back into I'll just do this or see it
wasn't a big deal
externally it was completely not a big
deal it was irrelevant but internally
he just uh you shut yourself in the foot
yet again and I have to heal and then
start again
it's like the example with the five
animals you tattoo
you you try to hold back initially but
then it gets too painful to use
oh I'm just let them go yeah yeah
there's nothing in between did you see
yeah yeah and that's that's the problem
and see if somebody starts to kind of
say no on the right level there is a
chance they can discern that middle
ground but if you refuse to even take on the
but if you refuse to even take on the
middle level because it's unpleasant to
begin with and just stick to I'll let
the animals go where others said
with others agreed we could feed
uh you're never going to take on that
internal dimensional practice that's
still about paramas in the nutshell
you're doing the the uh your Bound By
The Virtue and Duty in that external
sense that's why it's effectual feta
and like and see you can also see that
internally if whereby you review the
intention behind some actions and you
realize no this is done for good purpose
for increasing my practice for
increasing Solitude for decreasing
company for decreasing loss increasing
non-last but others might not approve of that
but others might not approve of that
they might they might find that uh
disagreeable then like I won't do it
then like I won't do it
so then I'll stay in what I've actually
know it's not as suitable
out of fear out of fear of being
criticize the blank
by those who obviously don't value the
same thing
so that's that's also a factor yeah
yeah and why would that be a factor well
because internally
you're afraid to be alone
you're afraid to take it on upon
yourself and recognize that it's up to
you and nobody else and nobody can come
in between it which is a good news and
bad news depending on how you look at it
but if you are finding shelter and
safety in the sense of camaraderie and
group in that sense Authority external
Authority or is highly discussed uh
impersonal they in them or we just
then it's like that's that's that's a
big problem because that will prevent
you from recognizing that middle ground
where the actual intentions and that
pasta and contact is all manifested
endured and where you are acting from
but you recognize the middle ground and
then it's not really far-fetched when
you read the suit as when the Buddha
said to some monks or nuns just whatever
you know it wholesome cultivate whatever
you know as unwholesome abandon it and
they became other hand as a result of
that
so I was like yeah because they found
the roots of wholesome and wholesome and
they actually abandoned it
needs to endure things under that level
for as long as that took
did not act
discerned honorability became apparent
maintained things fell into place
and this practice of reviewing your
actions so as I said initially it will
be on that level
but then say you are
training yourself to become
to Delight in solitude as the suitors
would say to to to to to find actually
to prefer
being alone to not mind living with your
own self and your mind internally that's
when in the same attitude same efforts
would apply and then you would be doing
it on the level of recognizing
hindrances and acting out of them
and acting out of them
because they are obviously fundamentally
internally bound
and so when you are withdrawn and you
have not been acting unwholesomely by
Body by speech
then yes you're going to start seeing
just the centrality on the mental level
Delight on the mental level
thoughts of ill will
that mental level sloth
laziness indolence
doubt anxiety
anxiety
and same you recognize there's a degree
of pressure
present a risen mind wants to act get
rid of it cover it up
to that extent you don't do it to that
extent you don't deny it
and train yourself in regard to that
newly discovered base threshold Middle
Ground and that's how you go beyond it
and that's how you go beyond it
when you are
firmly firm in the Middle Ground they
they cannot enter you anymore
okay another way of describing
going Beyond it being to understand its
nature so if you're acting out of it that's the
so if you're acting out of it that's the
antithesis of understanding its nature
yeah yeah so so not acting out of it or
denying it or denying it it's the form
working out again that would be uh that
would be the first step understanding
the nature
I don't think you necessarily most
people probably wouldn't you wouldn't
have to make specific effort because by
that time say if you are on the level of
being able to not act out of hindrances
to see them endure on that mental level
that remain composed uh that's already
by that time you already know the
certain nature of unability
dissatisfaction and that we're just
going to be seen there you know absorbed
by the content of it you're able to see
it as a hindrance yeah and the only
reason you will be absorbed by the
content of it is because you don't want
you don't like the touch you don't like
the pressure that it has over you so you
want to get rid of that yeah yeah that's
how you get involved so mounting it is
able to yeah yeah so when you are
unmoved by the pressure would say
would say
not like code contact does not appear no
there's no ground for contact that's
there to touch you